Guide to the Miscellaneous Literary Manuscripts and Correspondence
University of Houston Libraries
Miscellaneous Literary Manuscripts and Correspondence
1634-1991
1838-1991
1969-077
University of Houston. Libraries. Special Collections Department
0.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection is a result of integrating several items from Manuscripts A-Z into one artificial collection to improve organization and facilitate greater access. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, notes, and autographs belonging to various American and British literary figures from the 19th and 20th century (with one exception from 1634).
Historical Note:
Special Collections collects and preserves historically significant materials. Its holdings comprise a rare book collection and ten main archival collecting areas. In some instances, Special Collections gathers materials on a single topic to preserve them and make them available. In these cases, Special Collections is seen as the creator of the artificially constructed collection.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre)
Personal Name:
Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999; Bukowski, Charles; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925; De la Mare, Walter, 1873-1956; James, Henry, 1843-1916; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Thurber, James, 1894-1961
Topical Term:
Authors, American -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; Authors, English -- 19th century; Authors, English -- 20th century
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The collection is a result of integrating several items from Manuscripts A-Z into one artificial collection to improve organization and facilitate greater access. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, notes, and autographs belonging to various American and British literary figures from the 19th and 20th century (with one exception from 1634). The collection is arranged alphabetically by literary figure or, where author names are not available, title of piece.
Detailed List of Contents
- Sherwood Anderson, autograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Edwin Arnold, correspondence, 1887-1896 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "A Roundelay on April Day" song manuscript, anonymous, approximately 1850 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Paul Alexander Bartlett, letter to Anita McCormick Blaine, June 1, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Paul Bowles, three letters to Irving Stettner, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Richard Braithewaite, letter to Lord Spencer of Allthrope, November 4, 1634 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Charles Bukowski, letter to John, March 12, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- George Washington Cable, letter to Mrs. Blanchard, November 16, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Benjamin DeCasseres, letter to Mr. Roberts and various promotional materials, 1937, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Walter De La Mare, letter to Mr. Langdale, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- J. Floyd, "Account of the Hurricane or Whirlwind of the 8th of April" manuscript, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- George Milton Fowles, "Down in Porto Rico" manuscript, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- R.D. Frazier, "The Sailor's Horn-Book" manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- John Galsworthy, two letters, September 18, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Rudolph Gilbert, three letters to Mrs. Bliss, 1944, 1944, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Emerson Hough, letter to Welling Napton, June 3, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Norah Hoult and Evelyn Scot two letters, June, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Eugene Ionesco, autograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Henry James, letter to George Edward Barton, October 26, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Joseph Jacobs and DeWitt Miller, letter, April 14, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Sylvan Karchmer and Joanne Leedom-Ackerman, letter, June 4, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- E.V. Lucas, letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Robert Nathan, correspondence, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- A.F. Olmsted, "On Whirlwinds Produced by the Burning of a Cane-Brake in Alabama" manuscript, August, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Eugene ​O'Neill, letter to Mrs. Thomas Midgley, December 10, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Katherine Anne Porter, two letters, 1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Ezra Pound, "What America Has to Live Down" manuscript, August 22, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Ezra Pound, letter from Merrill Sparks, October 6, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Ezra Pound, photocopies of manuscript material, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Ezra Pound, handwritten notes on "The Genteel Tradition in Liberal Education" by Harold A. Taylor, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Lawrence Clark​ Powell, letter to Mr. J.E. Dolena, January 6, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Thomas Mayne​ Reid, two letters, 1879, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Edward Payson Roe, letter, January 6, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Gertrude Stein, "Doctor Faustus Lights the Lights" manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Algernon Charles Swinburne, signature, approximately 1900 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- James Thurber, "Josephine Has Her Day" from Adirondack Life, pg. 44, April 1991 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- James Thurber, pencil sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- James Thurber, three pen and ink sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- "To the Russians" poem, anonymous, June 2, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 39)